So, my name is Roger Doiron,
اسمي (روجر دوارين)،
and I have a subversive plot.
وأحيك مؤامرة تخريبية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It is so subversive, in fact,
إنها تخريبية للغاية، في الواقع،
that it has the potential to radically alter the balance of power,
حيث تستطيع أن تغير جذريًا ميزان القوى،
not only in our own country,
ليس في بلادنا فقط،
but in the entire world.
بل في العالم أجمع.
Now I realize, I'm sounding --
أدرك الآن أنني أبدو...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
a little bit like Dr. Evil now.
أبدو مثل (دكتور إيفل) الآن.
I understand that.
أتفهم هذا.
But trust me -- we have very, very little in common.
لكن صدقوني، لا نتقاسم الكثير من الأمور.
His plots are all about destruction and secrecy,
تتمحور مؤامراته حول التدمير والتكتم،
whereas my plots are about creation and openness.
بينما تتمحور مؤامراتي حول الإبداع والوضوح.
In fact, my plot can only work
في الواقع، تنجح مؤامرتي فقط
if I share it with as many people as possible.
إذا شاركتها مع أكبر عدد ممكن من الأشخاص.
So I'm going to share it with you now,
لذا، سأشاركها معكم الآن،
but you have to promise me you're going to share it in turn.
لكن عليكم أن تعدوني أنكم ستشاركونها بدوركم.
So here it is.
لذا، ها هي.
Huh. That's not so good, is it?
حسنًا، ليس هذا بالأمر الجيد، صحيح؟
There's nothing particularly radical or revolutionary about a patch of grass.
لا يوجد شيٌء جذريٌ أو ثوريُ بخصوص حزمة من العشب.
What starts to get interesting is when we turn it into this.
ويصبح الأمر مثيرًا للاهتمام عندما نحولها لهذا الشكل.
Now, I would like to suggest to you all
الآن، أود أن أوضح لكم جميعًا
that gardening is a subversive activity.
أن البستنة هي فعل تخريبي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Think about this: food is a form of energy.
فكروا في هذا: الطعام شكل من أشكال الطاقة.
It's what our body runs on,
هو ما يحرك أجسادنا،
but it's also a form of power.
لكنه أيضًا شكل من أشكال القوة.
And when we encourage people to grow some of their own food,
وعندما نشجع الناس على زراعة غذائهم الخاص،
we're encouraging them to take power into their hands,
نحن نشجعهم على امتلاك القوة بأيديهم،
power over their diet,
القوة حول نظامهم الغذائي،
power over their health
القوة حول صحتهم
and some power over their pocketbooks.
وبعض القوة حول حافظة أموالهم.
So I think that's quite subversive, because we're also necessarily
لذا أعتقد أن هذا نوعٌ من التخريب، لأنه أيضًا من الضروري
talking about taking that power away
الحديث عن أخذ تلك القوة
from someone else,
من شخص آخر،
from other actors in society that currently have power
من الأطراف الفاعلة في المجتمع، الذين يمتلكون القوة حاليًا
over food and health.
حول الغذاء والصحة.
You can think about who those actors might be.
يمكنكم التفكير عمن قد تكون هذه الأطراف.
I also look at gardening as a sort of healthy gateway drug,
أنا أيضًا أرى البستنة كنوع من الإدمان الصحي،
you might say, to other forms of food freedom.
يمكنكم القول أنها تتحول إلى شكل آخر من حرية الغذاء.
It's not long after you plant a garden
لن تأخذ منكم وقتًا طويلًا بعد زراعة حديقة
that you start to say, "Hey, I need to start to learn how to cook."
أن تبدأوا في القول: "حسنًا، أريد تعلم الطبخ."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"You know, I might want to look into food preservation
"كما تعلمون، قد أعمل على حفظ الأغذية
or I might want to look up where my local farmer's market
أو ربما البحث عن سوق المزارعين المحلي
is located in my town."
في مدينتي."
Now the other thing, of course, with planting a garden,
الشيء الآخر، بالطبع، المتعلق بزراعة حديقة،
especially a garden in front of a white house
خاصةً حديقة في مقدمة بيت أبيض
and on a sunny south lawn,
وفي بستان جنوبي مشمس،
is you never know who you might influence.
هو أنك لن تعرف أبدًا مَن الذين ستؤثر عليهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I'm not exactly sure what my white house garden's influence
الآن، لست واثقًا تمامًا من تأثير حديقتي في (البيت الأبيض)
was on the First Lady's,
على السيدة الأولى،
but I can tell you this:
لكن أستطيع القول:
she's had an enormous influence on me
تأثرتُ بها بشكل هائل
since planting hers.
منذ بدأت بزراعة حديقتها.
Now it hasn't been --
الآن لم تكن...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
it hasn't been in the area of fashion.
لم تكن في منطقة الموضة.
I understand that she's just in a completely different league there,
أتفهم أنها في مكانة مختلفة تمامًا
and I'm not even trying to compete.
ولست أحاول حتى أن أنافسها على هذا.
But she's really inspired me to think much more boldly
لكنها بالفعل ألهمتني لكي أفكر بجرأة أكبر
about the role that I want to have in the garden movement.
عن القاعدة التي أريدها في حركة الحدائق.
And so this is sort of what I'm aspiring to here.
وهذا هو ما أطمح إليه نوعًا ما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, pretty modest, right?
الآن، متواضع للغاية، صحيح؟
I like this picture.
أحب هذه الصورة.
I think it sort of captures me well,
أعتقد أنها تأسرني كثيرًا،
not that I have any divine connections whatsoever,
ليس لأنه لدي اهتمامات دينية،
but I like my facial expression there,
لكن أحب تعابير وجهي هناك،
because, if I've got a worried look on my face,
لأنه إذا بدا على وجهي القلق،
it's not simply because I've got 20 pounds of squash over my head,
ليس لأني أحمل 20 رطلًا من القرع فوق رأسي،
but it's because I've got some pretty heavy topics on my mind.
بل لأنه راودتني أفكار مهمة جدًا.
And I want to share some of those with you right now,
وأريد أن أشارك بعضها معكم الآن،
starting off in the form of a very short video I've produced for you,
بداية من فيديو قصير للغاية أعددته لكم،
which is my best effort to sum up the history of gastronomy
وهذا أفضل ما بذلته لتلخيص تاريخ فن الطهي
in about 15 seconds.
مدته حوالي 15 ثانية.
("Also sprach Zarathustra" plays)
(موسيقى)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, here we are.
إذن، ها نحن ذا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, that's a funny little clip,
هذا مقطع صغير ممتع،
but it'd be even funnier if it weren't so tragic
لكنه قد يصبح أكثر إمتاعًا إذا لم يكن مأساويًا هكذا
and if it weren't so true.
وإذا لم يكن حقيقيًا هكذا.
The reality is that we are in the midst of an obesity epidemic,
الحقيقة أننا في خضم وباء السمنة،
and it's not simply limited to our country.
ولا يقتصر هذا على بلادنا.
It's spreading around the world right now.
وينتشر في أرجاء العالم.
And in a sort of parallel universe,
وفي عالم متوازي نوعًا ما،
we're also seeing that hunger is on the rise.
نرى أن أزمة الجوع تتفاقم.
Over 900 million people right now are affected by it.
أكثر من 900 مليون شخص يعانون منه.
That's three times the population of the United States.
يمثل هذا 3 أضعاف سكان الولايات المتحدة.
But at the same time,
لكن في نفس الوقت،
world food prices are rising
تتزايد أسعار الغذاء العالمية
and world population is rising and is set to reach 10 billion people
وتتزايد أعداد السكان ومن المقدَّر أن يصلوا إلى 10 مليار نسمة
by the end of the century.
بحلول نهاية القرن.
Now, another thing about the population is we know that it's increasing,
الآن، نعلم أن أعداد السكان في زيادة،
but a lot of us don't realize that it's also changing.
لكن لا يدرك كثير منا أن هذا يتغير أيضًا.
There's a fundamental shift taking place.
يحدث هناك تحولًا جوهريًا.
As of 2007, we went from being a primarily rural planet
في عام 2007، انتقلنا من كوكب أساسه الزراعة
to being a primarily urban one,
إلى كوكب أساسه الصناعة،
and that has implications for how we're going to feed these people,
ولهذا دلالات عن كيفية توفير الغذاء لهؤلاء السكان،
how we're going to get the food to the people in the cities.
وكيفية توصيل الغذاء لقاطني المدن.
Now, I imagine that there are some Stephen King fans
أتخيل الآن وجود بعض معجبي (ستيفن كنج)
in the audience here,
من بين الجمهور هنا،
and I'm one of them.
وأنا واحد من معجبيه.
But I can tell you, I haven't read anything scarier than this here,
لكن أستطيع القول أنني لم أقرأ شيئًا مخيفًا أكثر من هذا،
and that's this statistic:
وهذه هي الإحصائيات:
in order to keep up with the growing population,
لكي نواكب أعداد السكان المتزايدة،
we're going to need to grow more food over the course of the next 50 years
سنحتاج أن نزرع المزيد من الغذاء على مدار الـ50 سنة القادمة
than we have grown over the course of the past 10,000 years combined.
أكثر مما زرعناه على مدى الـ10,000 سنة الماضية مجتمعة.
What makes this even more challenging
الذي يبعث أكثر على التحدي
is that we're going to need to grow all this food with less,
هو أننا سنحتاج زراعة كافة هذا الغذاء باستخدام موارد قليلة،
and when I say less,
وعندما أقول موارد قليلة،
I mean a number of things.
أعني عددًا من الأشياء.
Less oil, for example.
نفط أقل على سبيل المثال.
Most reputable geologists believe that we've already reached
يعتقد معظم علماء الجيولوجيا المرموقين أننا وصلنا بالفعل
peak oil production in the world.
لذروة الإنتاج النفطي في العالم.
Now, you might not think in terms of oil and food as being linked,
قد لا تفكروا في أن النفط والغذاء مرتبطان،
but there's a very strong link, in fact.
لكن هناك رابطًا قويًا في الواقع.
It takes 10 calories of fossil fuel energy
يتطلب الأمر 10 سعرات من طاقة الوقود الحفري
in our highly industrialized food system
في نظامنا الغذائي عالي التصنيع
in order to produce one calorie of food energy.
لكي ننتج سُعرًا واحدًا من الطاقة الغذائية.
We'll also need to grow more food with less water.
سنحتاج أيضًا إلى زراعة غذاء أكثر باستخدام مياه أقل.
These three images come from three very different parts of the planet,
التقطت هذه الصور الثلاثة من مناطق مختلفة على الكوكب،
but they all tell the same story of catastrophic drought.
لكن تعود جميعها لنفس الجفاف الكارثي.
We'll also need to grow more food with less farmland.
سنحتاج أيضًا إلى زراعة الغذاء باستخدام أراضي زراعية أقل.
Here, the pressures differ from one place to the next.
هنا، يختلف الضغط من مكان لآخر.
In the Global South, we're seeing desertification,
في نصف الكرة الجنوبي، نرى التصحر،
whereas in the north, we're seeing suburban sprawl.
بينما في الشمال، نرى الزحف العمراني.
We'll also have to grow more food with less climate stability
سنحتاج أيضًا إلى زراعة الغذاء في ظل استقرار مناخي أقل
and less genetic diversity.
وتنوع وراثي أقل.
Now, this is really important.
الآن، هذا مهم للغاية.
We need our genetic varieties
نحتاج إلى الأصناف الوراثية
because they're a sort of insurance policy against climate change.
لأنها تعد بوليصة تأمين ضد تغير المناخ.
We heard earlier today
سمعنا سابقًا
"not putting all of our eggs in one basket."
"لا تضع كل ما تملك من البيض في سلة واحدة."
Well, we shouldn't be doing the same with our tomatoes, either.
حسنًا، لا يجب أن نفعل المثل مع الطماطم أيضًا.
We're also going to need to grow more food with less time.
سنحتاج أيضًا إلى زراعة المزيد من الغذاء في وقت أقل.
Now here, I'm not simply talking about the ticking time bomb
لا أتحدث ببساطة عن القنبلة الموقوتة
that is the global population.
ألا وهي سكان المعمورة.
I'm talking about the amount of time we all have
أتحدث عن كمية الوقت التي لدينا
in order to put a decent meal on the table.
لكي نضع وجبة لائقة على المائدة.
And that "31" figure there is not something arbitrary.
وأن رقم "31" ليس رقمًا عشوائيًا.
That's the average amount of time the American family spends
هذا هو متوسط الفترة الزمنية التي تقضيها عائلة أمريكية
preparing, eating and cleaning up after meals per day.
في إعداد الطعام وتناوله وتنظيف ما بعد الوجبات يوميًا.
31 minutes.
31 دقيقة.
So somewhere in there, we're going to need to also fit in growing food.
في مكان ما، نحتاج أيضًا إلى ملاءمة زراعة الغذاء.
Alright?
صحيح؟
And I think we do need to do that,
وأعتقد أننا بحاجة لفعل ذلك،
but that's also going to mean that somewhere along the way,
لكن هذا يعني أنه في مرحلة ما،
something's going to have to give.
لن نستطيع الاستمرار على هذا النحو.
So it sort of leaves us feeling like this.
لذا سنشعر هكذا في النهاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know?
أتعرفون؟
It's time to leave town or even perhaps leave planets.
حان الوقت لمغادرة المدينة أو حتى ربما مغادرة الكوكب.
But where do we go?
لكن أين نذهب؟
Where do we go when we only have one planet?
أين نذهب في حين ليس لدينا مكان غيره؟
And where do we go where the going gets tough?
وأين نذهب حيثما يصبح الذهاب شاقًا؟
Well, if we were to listen to a lot of our political leaders over the years,
حسنًا، إذا كنا سنستمع لقادتنا السياسيين على مدى السنوات،
we would simply go shopping.
سنذهب ببساطة للتسوق.
Right?
صحيح؟
Because we have this unwavering belief,
لأننا لدينا هذا الاعتقاد الراسخ،
especially in American political culture,
خاصةً في الثقافة السياسية الأمريكية،
that we can shop our way out of just about any problem.
أننا نستطيع التسوق كحل لأي مشكلة.
But the reality is something different.
لكن الواقع مختلف تمامًا.
We're not going to solve our food problems and our health problems
لن نحل مشكلاتنا الغذائية والصحية
simply by switching from regular Coke
ببساطة عن طريق تغيير (الكوكا) العادية
to some future green iteration thereof.
إلى تكرار نسخة منها لمستقبل أخضر.
And although the large food companies would like us to believe
وعلى الرغم من أن الشركات الغذائية الكبرى تريدنا أن نصدّق
that we can give our children all of the vitamins, minerals
أننا نستطيع إعطاء أطفالنا الفيتامينات والمعادن
and immunity-building substances that they need
ومواد بناء المناعة التي يحتاجونها
without even leaving the chocolatey cereal aisle --
بدون ترك ممرّ حبوب الشكولاتة،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
the truth is something quite different.
الحقيقة مختلفة إلى حد ما.
Now, what's become even more troublesome of late
والذي أصبح أكثر إزعاجًا مؤخرًا
is that even the foods that ought to be healthy aren't always so,
هو أن الأغذية الصحية لا تكون هكذا دائمًا،
and we're starting to lose confidence in our food system, I think.
وبدأنا في فقدان الثقة في نظامنا الغذائي.
The bigger it becomes and the more complex it becomes.
كلما أصبح أكبر، كلما أصبح أكثر تعقيدًا.
And we've seen this time and time again.
وقد رأينا ذلك مرارًا وتكرارًا.
This is an image from the latest E. coli outbreak.
هذه صورة من أحدث انتشار لفيروس (إي كولي).
In this case, it was in Europe,
في هذه الحالة، كان في (أوروبا)،
and we think it was started with bean sprouts, of all things.
ونحن نعتقد أنه بدأ ببراعم الفول.
So we have this sort of shopper's dilemma right now.
لذا نواجه معضلة خاصة بالمتسوقين.
We have all of these different foods --
لدينا مختلف الأغذية،
30,000 foods in the average big-box grocery store --
30,000 نوع غذائي في متجر بقالة كبير،
but we have less confidence in those foods,
لكننا لا نثق في هذه الأطعمة.
and we have less confidence in the actors
ولا نثق في الأطراف
that are putting those foods on the shelves.
التي تضع هذه الأطعمة على الرفوف.
I think we need to redefine what good food is.
أعتقد أنه علينا إعادة تحديد الغذاء الجيد.
This is an interesting image from Berlin, Germany,
هذه صورة مثيرة للاهتمام من (برلين، ألمانيا).
where somebody started planting shopping carts and leaving them around.
حيث بدأ شخص ما في زراعة عربات التسوق وتركها في الأرجاء.
Those are potatoes, by the way.
هذا محصول البطاطس بالمناسبة.
But in addition to redefining what good food is,
لكن مع إعادة تحديد الغذاء الجيد،
I think we need to redefine our living spaces.
أعتقد أننا نحتاج إلى إعادة تحديد مساحات حياتنا.
Instead of seeing this as a yard,
بدلًا من رؤية هذه كساحة فناء،
we need to think of it more as like a full-service greengrocer.
علينا أن نفكر فيها كمتجر كامل الخدمات.
That's, in fact, my yard, and that's how I look at it.
هذه في الواقع ساحة فنائي وأراها بهذه الطريقة.
That's what we transformed our yard into,
هذا هو الشكل الذي حولنا إليه الساحة،
and I think a really key message is this one:
وأعتقد بالفعل أن الرسالة الأساسية هي:
gardens grow good food.
ينمو بالحدائق غذاء جيد.
And when I say good food,
وعنندما أقول غذاءََ جيدًا،
I mean a number of different things.
أعني مجموعة أشياء مختلفة.
I mean food that is safe,
أعني أن الغذاء آمن،
food that is healthy,
وأنه صحي،
food that is absolutely gorgeous
وأنه فائق الجمال
and delicious.
وطعمه شهي.
Another important message is this one:
يوجد رسالة أخرى مهمة:
gardens grow healthy kids and families.
الحدائق تساعد على نمو صحي للأطفال والعائلات.
Those happen to be my two youngest sons,
يصادف أنهما ابناي الصغيرين،
and they look healthy and they are healthy,
ويبدو عليهما أنهما بصحة جيدة وهما كذلك،
and I think it has to do with the fact that they grew up in gardens
وأعتقد أن هذا له صلة أنهما ترعرعا في الحدائق
and they know where good food comes from.
ويعلمان مصدر الغذاء الجيد.
And in fact, they know how to grow some of it themselves.
وفي الواقع يعلمان كيفية زراعته بأنفسهم.
But in the current economy, I think it's key to get this message out,
لكن في ظل الاقتصاد الراهن، أعتقد من المهم أن ننشر هذه الرسالة،
that gardens also grow important economic savings for families.
أن الحدائق أيضًا توفر مدخرات اقتصادية مهمة للعائلات.
And you can pretty much take my word on this one,
وبإمكانكم الوثوق بكلامي للغاية،
because in addition to crunching the vegetables a couple of years ago,
لأنه بالإضافة لاستهلاك الخضروات منذ بضعة أعوام،
my wife and I also crunched the numbers,
أجريت أنا وزوجتي حسابات الأرقام،
and we found out that at the end,
واكتشفنا ذلك في النهاية،
we had saved well over 2,000 dollars by growing our own food.
ادخرنا أكثر من 2,000 دولار من زراعة غذائنا الخاص.
So you could be asking this question now:
لذا قد تطرحون هذا السؤال الآن:
If gardens grow all of these great things, how do we grow more gardens?
إذا كانت هذه الأشياء المذهلة تنمو بالحدائق فكيف نزرع المزيد من الحدائق؟
That's, in fact, the question that my organization,
هذا السؤال الذي تطرحه مؤسستي،
Kitchen Gardens International,
(كتشن جاردنز انترناشونال)،
is both asking and answering.
وتجيب عنه في نفس الوقت.
And our answer is essentially this one:
وهذه إجابتنا بشكل أساسي:
we're going to need to leverage the resources and power that we have,
نحتاج إلى تعزيز الموارد والقوة التي لدينا،
the gardens and gardeners that we have,
الحدائق والبستانيين العاملين فيها،
in order to grow and inspire even more.
لكي نزرع المزيد من الحدائق ونلهم آخرين لزراعتها.
And as I said before, you never know who you might inspire.
وكما قلت سابقًا، لا أحد يعلم مَن قد تلهمون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now if this campaign was successful,
إذا قدّر لهذه الحملة النجاح،
I think it wasn't simply because we had a visionary First Lady
أعتقد ليس لأننا حظينا بسيدة أولى ملهمة
taking up residence at the White House --
تقيم في (البيت الأبيض)،
that certainly was a major part of it --
وهذا كان عاملًا مهمًا في نجاحها،
and it wasn't simply because we had some celebrity chefs and authors
وليس لأن بعض مشاهير الطهاة والكتّاب
saying this would be a good idea to do.
يرددون أن هذه الفكرة جيدة لتنفيذها.
I think it was ultimately made possible
أعتقد أن النجاح كان ممكنًا
by the fact that there were a lot of people who wanted it to happen.
بسبب حقيقة أن كثيرين أرادوا لها ذلك.
There was a movement that made it happen.
كانت هناك حركة جعلتها تتحقق.
And my organization tried to sort of channel some of that energy
وحاولت مؤسستي تحويل تلك الطاقة
of the movement
النابعة من الحركة
and direct it towards the White House.
وتوجيهها نحو (البيت الأبيض).
And we had a lot of luck
وحالفنا الحظ كثيرًا
in terms of getting our message out there to the media.
من حيث وصول رسالتنا إلى الإعلام.
We had a petition on Facebook, 110,000 signatures.
كان لدينا عريضة على (فيسبوك) وقع عليها 110,000 شخص.
We had viral images and videos,
انتشرت العديد من الصور والفيديوهات،
and we did crazy things like symbolically putting the White House lawn
وقمنا بأشياء جنونية مثل عرْض حديقة (البيت الأبيض) بشكل رمزي
up for sale on eBay.
للبيع على موقع (إيباي).
But we need to do even more,
لكننا نحتاج القيام بالمزيد،
and what we're trying to do in my organization
وما نحاول فعله في مؤسستي
is to connect people online,
هو تواصل الناس عبر الانترنت،
but also to connect people in person.
وأيضًا تواصلهم بشكل شخصي.
This is an image from a little holiday we invented
هذه صورة عن عطلة صغيرة دعينا الناس إليها
called "World Kitchen Garden Day."
اسمها "يوم حدائق المطبخ العالمي."
It's at the end of August each year,
يقام في نهاية أغسطس من كل عام،
and it's just about bringing people together in gardens
ويتمحور حول جمع الناس ببعضهم في الحدائق
to learn from one another,
لكي يتبادلوا المعرفة،
to experience a garden as a community experience.
وتجربة الحدائق على أنها خبرة مجتمعية.
We also need to grow the next generation of gardeners,
علينا أيضًا بناء الجيل القادم من البستانيين،
and we're doing that in the United States and abroad.
ونفعل ذلك في (الولايات المتحدة) وخارجها.
But there's still so much more that needs to be done,
لكن يظل هناك الكثير لنفعله،
and I think this slide sort of captures where we need to go.
وأظن أن هذه الشريحة ترشدنا للوجهة التي علينا أن نسلكها.
We need a road map,
نحتاج إلى وضع خريطة طريق،
and I picked this slide for a reason.
وأخذت هذه الشريحة لسبب وجيه.
We've got a bike garden on the left
لدينا حديقة من الدراجات على اليسار.
and a map of the Netherlands on the right.
وخريطة (هولندا) على اليمين.
I was in the Netherlands early this year
قصدتُ (هولندا) في مطلع هذا العام
and was absolutely amazed by the amount of bikes on the road;
وكنت مندهشًا للغاية من وجود هذا العدد من الدراجات على قارعة الطريق؛
26 percent of all trips taken in the Netherlands are by bicycle,
26% من الرحلات في (هولندا) تُقطع بواسطة الدراجات،
and it's gotten me thinking:
وجعلني هذا أفكر:
How do we get that happening in terms of food and gardens?
كيف نطبّق ذلك في مجال الغذاء والحدائق؟
How would we get 26 percent of all produce coming from backyard gardens?
كيف نحصل على 26% من المنتجات الصادرة من الحدائق الخلفية للمنازل؟
That might sound like a lot,
قد تبدو هذه النسبة كبيرة،
because we're probably at about two percent at the most right now.
لأننا وصلنا لنسبة 2% كحد أقصى حتى الآن.
But if you take into consideration
لكن إذا وضعتم في عين الاعتبار
that at the peak of the victory garden movement last century,
أن في قمة انتصار حركة الحدائق في القرن الماضي،
40 percent of all produce was coming from gardens.
40% من المنتجات كانت صادرة من الحدائق.
We can get there again.
نستطيع الوصول لتلك النسبة مرة أخرى.
And I think this is a really good start.
وأعتقد أن هذه ستكون بداية جيدة.
The White House garden is certainly very inspirational.
حديقة (البيت الأبيض) كانت بالتأكيد ملهمة للغاية.
That's actually sort of a snapshot of what the garden looked like
هذه في الواقع صورة عن شكل الحديقة
when it was planted earlier this spring --
عندما زرعت في بداية هذا الربيع،
lots of diversity, lots of healthy crops.
كثير من التنوع والمحاصيل الصحية.
However, this is not a good representation
برغم ذلك، لم يكن هذا تمثيلًا جيدًا
of our federal agriculture policy.
للسياسة الفيدرالية الزراعية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If we were to take the model here, the diagram of that particular garden,
إذا أخذنا هذا النموذج هنا، الرسم البياني لتلك الحديقة تحديدًا،
and sort of transpose it onto our federal agriculture policy,
ونقلناه إلى سياسة الزراعة الفيدرالية،
we'd get this:
نحصل على هذه النتيجة:
billions of billions of dollars going to support
تذهب مليارات الدولارات لدعم
just a handful of commodity crops
مجموعة من محاصيل السلع
with just that tiny little bit at the top for fruits and vegetables.
بدعم صغير في الأعلى يذهب للفاكهة والخضروات.
This is scandalous. This is scandalous.
هذا أمر مخز للغاية. مخز للغاية.
We need to do something about this.
لابد من فعل شيء ما بخصوص هذا.
I think one place we could start is we could look at the tax code.
أظن أن المكان الوحيد الذي نستطيع البدء منه هو النظر إلى قانون الضرائب.
We're already using the tax code to encourage green transport
نحن بالفعل نستخدم قانون الضرائب لأجل تشجيع النقل الملائم للبيئة
and green shelter.
والسكن الملائم للبيئة.
Why not green food?
لم لا يتوفر غذاء ملائم للبيئة؟
We're in the midst now of talking about another stimulus package.
نحن في خضم الحديث عن مجموعة حوافز أخرى.
Why not a garden stimulus package?
لم لا تتوفر مجموعة حوافز خاصة بالحدائق؟
Why not?
لم لا؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In terms of other things that we need to be doing,
والأشياء الأخرى التي علينا فعلها،
we need to move down to the local level
نحتاج للتحرك نزولًا للمستوى المحلي
and we need to make sure that gardens are legal.
ونحتاج للتأكد من أن الحدائق قانونية.
This is an illegal garden. At least it was.
هذه حديقة غير قانونية. على الأقل كانت هكذا.
It's from Michigan earlier this year.
هذه من (ميتشيغان) في بداية هذا العام.
It was planted by a woman, a mother of four,
زرعتها امرأة وأم لأربعة أبناء،
and she nearly faced a 93-day jail sentence
كادت أن تواجه عقوبة بالسجن لمدة 93 يومًا
because she planted it in her front yard.
لأنها زرعت فنائها الأمامي.
We still have laws from the 20th century.
ما زلنا نطبق قوانين من القرن الـ20.
We need to bring our codes up to the realities that we are facing now.
علينا أن نصدر قوانين تواكب الواقع الذي نعيشه.
We need to figure out also new ways of getting people into gardens,
علينا اكتشاف طرق جديدة لاستثمار الناس بالحدائق،
people who don't have yards.
الأشخاص الذين لا يملكون أفنية.
I think we also need to set garden entrepreneurism free,
أظن أنه علينا إطلاق ريادة أعمال الحدائق،
and I'm happy to say, as a Mainer,
ويسعدني القول بصفتي من ولاية (مين)،
that we are leading the way in this area.
أننا تولينا دورًا قياديًا في هذا المجال.
Earlier this year, a number of Maine towns
في بداية هذا العام، قامت مجموعة من مدن (مين)
passed local food sovereignty laws
بتمرير قوانين سيادة الغذاء المحلي
that allow town residents to not only grow food
التي لا تسمح لقاطني المدن بزراعة الغذاء فقط
where they want to grow it
في المكان الذي يريدونه
but to also sell it the way they want to sell it
بل أيضًا تسمح ببيعه بالطريقة التي يريدونها
and to the people they want to sell it to.
للأشخاص الذين يرغبون بالبيع لهم.
I think that's an incentive.
أعتقد أن هذا يعد عاملًا محفزًا.
There are a lot of gardeners out there
يوجد هناك العديد من البستانيين
that would be interested in scaling up their production if they could,
الذين يبدون اهتمامًا تجاه زيادة إنتاجهم إذا كان في مقدورهم،
if they had a financial incentive.
إذا كانوا يمتلكون الحافز المادي.
I also think that we need to examine
أعتقد أيضًا أننا نحتاج لدراسة
the composition of the movement right now.
تشكيل الحركة الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If the movement were a 1960s beach flick,
إذا كانت الحركة مثل شاطيء في الستينات،
it would be "Where The Boys Aren't."
كان سيطلق عليها اسم "الأولاد في كل مكان."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I'm going to take you to task, guys.
سوف أكلفكم بمهمة يا رفاق.
It's not right and it's not fair that the burden of this responsibility --
ليس صائبًا أو عادلًا أن يتحمل عبء هذه المسؤولية...
feeding our country and the world --
وهي توفير الغذاء لبلادنا وللعالم...
should be with the women.
أن تتحملها النساء وحدهن.
OK?
حسنًا؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I'm going to challenge the women
وسأتحدى النساء
to come up with really clever, creative ways of getting guys
بأنهن سيجدن طرقًا بارعة وإبداعية لجعل الرجال
into the gardens, too.
يهتمون بالحدائق أيضًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Perhaps wearing a bathing suit?
ربما بارتداء ثوب سباحة؟
But beyond that, I think we need to reexamine the infrastructure
علاوة على ذلك، أعتقد أننا نحتاج لإعادة فحص البنية التحتية
that we have in place for gardens.
التي لدينا من أجل الحدائق.
I think we need to create new infrastructure.
أعتقد أنه علينا إنشاء بنية تحتية جديدة.
And this is one of the things my organization is working on right now,
وهذه أحد الأشياء التي تعمل عليها مؤسستي الآن،
sort of a local communications infrastructure, very place-based,
البنية التحتية للاتصالات المحلية القائمة على تحديد المكان،
that allows people in the same area to connect with one another
التي تسمح لسكان نفس المنطقة بالتواصل فيما بينهم
and to help each other out.
وتقديم المساعدة لبعضهم البعض.
I think we're lacking this at the moment --
أرى أنه ينقصنا هذا الأمر حاليًا...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but we can do it.
لكن بوسعنا فعل ذلك.
The technology is certainly there.
التكنولوجيا بالتأكيد متاحة.
In addition to that, I think we need another type of infrastructure.
إضافةً لذلك، أرى أننا نحتاج لنوع آخر من البنية التحتية.
It would be good if we could all get together.
سيكون رائعًا لو اتحدنا سويًا.
I think if we've learned anything through the TED experience,
أرى أنه إذا تعلمنا شيئًا خلال تجربة TED،
it's that there is power when we bring people together,
حينها ستسود قوة الجمع بين الناس،
and I think we need to bring people together at the local level as well.
وأعتقد أننا في حاجة لجمع الناس على المستوى المحلي أيضًا.
And I think we can take some inspiration from a previous movement,
وأعتقد أنه يمكننا استلهام الحركة السابقة،
which was the grange movement,
مثل حركة (جرانج)،
a rural movement which brought farmers together in a single building
وهي حركة ريفية جمعت بين المزارعين في مبنى واحد
to meet and to recreate and learn how to become better farmers.
للالتقاء وإيجاد الطرق وتعلّمها ليصبحوا مزارعين أفضل.
I think we need a network
أظن أننا بحاجة لإيجاد شبكة
of suburban granges now.
للمزارعين في الضواحي.
I think one of the last things that we need
وأرى أن واحدًا من آخر الأشياء التي نحتاجها
is to not lose the fun of food.
هو أن لا نفقد متعة الغذاء.
Food is at its best when it's delicious but shared as part of a community,
يكون الغذاء أفضل عندما يكون لذيذًا لكن مشاركته كجزء من المجتمع،
and I think that gardens can get some of that community vibe back as well.
أعتقد أن الحدائق يمكن أن تعيد شعور المجتمع إلى ما كان عليه.
So I'm going to leave with one last video,
سأدعكم لمشاهدة فيديو أخير،
and I'm going to revisit the short video that I showed you before,
وسأعيد تشغيل الفيديو الذي عرضته سابقًا،
but I'm going to suggest an alternative ending.
لكني سأعرض نهاية بديلة.
And I think this ending is well within our reach,
وأعتقد أن تحقيق هذه النهاية في متناول أيدينا،
but it's really going to require that we all pull together.
لكن سيتطلب ذلك تعاوننا جميعًا.
So here's the new history of gastronomy.
لذا إليكم تاريخًا جديدًا في فن الطهي
("Also sprach Zarathustra" plays)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Applause and cheers)
(تصفيق وهتافات)
Thank you very much. Thank you all. Thank you.
شكرًا جزيلًا. أشكركم جميعًا. شكرًا.